<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ruby | dgms code]]></title>
  <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/categories/ruby/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-25T12:27:26+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Duncan Stuart]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[dgmstuart@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ben Orenstein: Live Coding in the Bath at BathRuby]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2015/03/13/ben-orenstein-live-coding-in-the-bath-at-bathruby/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-13T10:34:52+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2015/03/13/ben-orenstein-live-coding-in-the-bath-at-bathruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I&rsquo;m at <a href="http://2015.bathruby.org/">Bath Ruby 2015</a>, live blogging some of the
talks</em></p>

<ul>
<li>Live coding!</li>
<li>Code for sending mail to a list of recipients based on a csv</li>
<li>Problems:

<ul>
<li>Will fail if one of the recipients fails to get parsed</li>
<li>CSV should get injected as a dependency rather than bring parsed in this
class.</li>
<li>Class has multiple responsibilities: parsing and mailing</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>TDD: Should take very little time and effort to run tests (his are two
keystrokes and no time)</li>
<li><p>an &lsquo;extract class&rsquo; refactoring:</p>

<ol>
<li>add the class we  want in the initialiser</li>
<li>create an empty spec</li>
<li>create the class</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><p><code>CSV::strip_heredoc</code> - Look up</p></li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t write specs for private methods - test them implicitly through the
public methods</li>
<li>Spec style for parsing output:

<ol>
<li>create a csv string</li>
<li>create an output hash</li>
<li>expect parsing the csv string to equal the output hash</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>TDD approach - do only the smalles thing to get the message to change: e.g.
create initializer with no args, then add one arg, then start to define
behaviour</li>
<li>Now actually use the parser.</li>
<li>Tests green = OVERWHELMING INSTINCT TO COMMIT!</li>
<li>&ldquo;Component test&rdquo; = integration test just covering a selection of components
(?)</li>
<li>Test refactoring: extract methods! (e.g. to do repeated stubbing and other
setup)

<ul>
<li>could use <code>before</code>, but tends to do this later or not at all. Makes specs
harder to read and maintain (?): each spec is different. Extracting method is definitely the first
step.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>&ldquo;We make a mess first, then we clean it up&rdquo;</li>
<li>Invert control: it&rsquo;s odd that we pass the csv into the Invitations class

<ul>
<li>Instead, &ldquo;build dependencies at higher level and pass it down to lower
levels&rdquo; (??)</li>
<li>Instead of passing the csv to invitations and creating a parser based on
it, let&rsquo;s send invitations to the parser (!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Inverting control benefits:

<ul>
<li>Easier to follow Open/Closed principle</li>
<li>Shorter specs</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Question &ldquo;The specs passed from the beginning, so weren&rsquo;t you done?&rdquo;

<ul>
<li>Answer: Refactoring makes more flexible maintainable code</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bath Ruby: Linda Liukas - Principles of Play]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2015/03/13/bath-ruby-linda-liukas-principles-of-play/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-13T09:42:26+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2015/03/13/bath-ruby-linda-liukas-principles-of-play</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I&rsquo;m at <a href="http://2015.bathruby.org/">Bath Ruby 2015</a>, live blogging some of the
talks</em></p>

<p><img src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/B_-CEvAWEAA1Fqu.jpg:large" alt="Photo of Linda Liukas by
@Naomi_Freeman" /></p>

<p><em>photo by <a href="https://twitter.com/naomi_freeman/">@Naomi_Freeman</a></em></p>

<ul>
<li>Railsgirls in over 277(?) cities

<ul>
<li>Started in Helsinki</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>&ldquo;The most scalable change in the world happens when you&rsquo;re 4 years old&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;If you draw 1000 circles eventually your circles will get better&rdquo;</li>
<li>Realtity distortion: being in the community allowed her to think &ldquo;Hey I can
write a children&rsquo;s book, even though I don&rsquo;t know how to draw, or write a
book, or program very well</li>
<li>3 principles of learning: Playfulness, Curiosity, Rules</li>
<li>Learning Real-world languages (Finnish) by reading other people&rsquo;s texts, not
by learning grammar rules first</li>
<li>&ldquo;Little girls don&rsquo;t know the are not supposed to like computers&rdquo;</li>
<li>Two joys of programming: 1. Building beautiful elegant proper things 2.
trying things which you&rsquo;re not sure will work and thrilling when it actually
works. This second one is the playfulness (what she&rsquo;s focussing on&#8221;</li>
<li>3 components of learning: Achievement, Social and Immersion. Traditional
learning mainly just focusses on the first</li>
<li>Rules: <em>how</em> do things work. &ldquo;Imposing logic on something otherwise hard to
understand&rdquo;</li>
<li>Teaching through metaphors: baking cupcakes - if you change the recipe
you&rsquo;ll get different cupcakes.</li>
<li>Curiosity: Asking <em>why</em>

<ul>
<li>Introduce 5 year olds to the idea that any object (cars, dogs, toilets)
could have a computer in it</li>
<li>Opening up to asking questions: &ldquo;what <em>happens</em> when I press play&rdquo;, &ldquo;is
the internet a place&rdquo; - these sort of questions which many adults don&rsquo;t
really
ask</li>
<li>Making computers out of paper - totally open thinking: this button prints
out lego - that button makes breakfast.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>__why&rsquo;s poignant guide etc. - opens up to this idea that people in
programming can be whimsical, human - not what an initial picture of
programming might be like</li>
<li>Programmers have found the loophole: we are the world-builders: making
something out of nothing using just words: Programming as Storytelling</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting Up a Ruby Dev Environment on Bowery.io]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2015/02/28/setting-up-a-ruby-on-rails-dev-environment-on-bowery-dot-io/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-28T01:27:44+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2015/02/28/setting-up-a-ruby-on-rails-dev-environment-on-bowery-dot-io</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>EDIT: Apparently it&rsquo;s not possible to run docker inside a Bowery instance
because Bowery uses docker and docker has a hard time running inside a docker
container - see <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/bowery/WsXWzWghwVc">this post on the forum</a></em></p>

<p><a href="http://bowery.io/">Bowery.io</a> is a hosted development environment service.
The idea is that you edit your files locally, but run your code in a cloud-hosted
<a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a> container, based on an image which can be
shared and edited by teams.</p>

<p>It looks like it used to host its own packages and allow environments to be
set up through a gui, but now the approach is to either install everything by
hand or use a dockerfile, which I guess makes sense as docker has become more
and more popular and Bowery&rsquo;s main audience is going to be quite devvy devs
who are comfortable using docker.</p>

<p>I had a go at setting up an environment for ruby development and didn&rsquo;t really
find any documentation so here&rsquo;s what I tried:</p>

<h2>Approach: Use a dockerfile</h2>

<p>The simplest way to start your Bowery image with ruby is to use a dockerfile
which sets ruby up for you. This can be as simple as creating a file called
<code>Dockerfile</code> at the root of your project, consisting of this line:</p>

<pre><code>from ruby:2.2.0
</code></pre>

<p>&hellip;then when you select your code directory for the first time through the
Bowery app you can click &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; on this prompt to initialize your Bowery image
based on that Dockerfile:</p>

<p><img src="/images/content/bowery_prompt.png"></p>

<p>More details about this approach can be found <a href="http://bowery.io/posts/dockerfile-support/">on the Bowery blog</a></p>

<h2>Approach: Install ruby directly</h2>

<p>Not having ever used docker in anger, my first attempt involved just
installing ruby manually. The following steps are
basically a textbook set of steps for installing ruby on a new Ubuntu machine
(which is what Bowery instances are based on):</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Update apt-get:</p>

<pre><code> apt-get update
</code></pre></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/sstephenson/ruby-build/wiki#suggested-build-environment">Install the dependencies for ruby-build</a>
using apt-get</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/sstephenson/rbenv">Install rbenv</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/sstephenson/ruby-build">Install ruby-build</a></p></li>
<li><p>Install ruby with rbenv:</p>

<pre><code> rbenv install 2.2.0
 rbenv global 2.2.0
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Install bundler:</p>

<pre><code> gem install bundler
</code></pre></li>
</ol>


<h2>What about Rails?</h2>

<p>I <em>have</em> managed to successfully set up a Rails dev environment using Bowery,
but it ended up being pretty fiddly and I&rsquo;m not sure I have anything coherent
enough to blog about.</p>

<p>I essentially set it up just like any other ubuntu box would be set up (but
I&rsquo;m still pretty green at server management - hence fiddly).</p>

<p>What I was hoping
to find was a Dockerfile which at least set up Ruby and Postgres, but it seems
like the normal approach is to run separate Docker containers and link them
(as in <a href="http://allenwei.cn/setup-rails-development-environment-with-docker/">this tutorial</a>).
I don&rsquo;t think this approach applies to Bowery, where a single dockerfile is
used to initialize the image. I suppose I could run docker on Bowery though? (#meta)</p>

<p>In any case, here are the additional components which need to be installed to
run my Rails dev environment:</p>

<ul>
<li>A Javascript runtime (I installed Node.js with apt-get)</li>
<li>A database (I installed Postgresql with apt-get but had a pain setting it up)</li>
<li>A headless browser for javascript specs (I <a href="http://phantomjs.org/build.html">built phantom.js from
scratch</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Migrating Postgres Data From an Old Rails Project to a New One]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/08/20/migrating-postgres-data-from-an-old-rails-project-to-a-new-one/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-20T23:29:31+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/08/20/migrating-postgres-data-from-an-old-rails-project-to-a-new-one</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>TL;DR - this was my approach:</p>

<ol>
<li>create migrations on the old project to transform the data into the new schema structure</li>
<li>run these migrations on a dump of the live database</li>
<li>dump just the data of the tables you care about from the migrated database with pg_dump</li>
<li>import this dump into the new database with psql</li>
</ol>


<p>Once I worked through a few kinks, it was all remarkably straightforward.</p>

<h2>Background</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dgmstuart/Swing-Out-London">Swing Out London</a> is a cms for managing swing events</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m rebuilding it from scratch as <a href="https://github.com/dgmstuart/swingoutlondon2">a totally new project</a></li>
<li>In particular the <a href="https://github.com/dgmstuart/Swing-Out-London/blob/274f64e1d635bcd8d2678eb6a0dfa50516ef64ba/db/schema.rb">old data model</a> was insane and the <a href="https://github.com/dgmstuart/swingoutlondon2/blob/daa4397f1e9d772a5b5302cdd369b81201c8ec84/db/schema.rb">new one</a>  is turning out much cleaner</li>
<li>The current live system is Rails 3 and hosted on Heroku - so uses postgres for the live database, but uses sqlite for the development database</li>
<li>The new system is Rails 4 and uses postgres for the development database</li>
</ul>


<p>I want to be able to import data from the current live site into my work-in-progress new schema as I go along, for a few reasons:</p>

<ol>
<li>Doing the migration incrementally will hopefully be easier than doing it all in one go at the end</li>
<li>Working with real data will help me make better design decisions earlier</li>
<li>Being able to see what is missing between the old and new schemas will help to make sure I don&rsquo;t miss anything</li>
</ol>


<h2>The challenge</h2>

<p>Data which in the old app exists in one god object (<code>event</code>) needs to be divided between three tables in the new app (<code>events</code>, <code>event_seeds</code>, <code>event_generators</code>).</p>

<p>In particular, in the new app, events with individual dates are modelled by having:</p>

<ul>
<li>an <code>event_generator</code> with a date, which belongs to&hellip;</li>
<li>an <code>event_seed</code> (which holds the main data) and belongs to&hellip;</li>
<li>an <code>event</code> which groups <code>event_seed</code>s together.</li>
</ul>


<p>In the old app, dates are stored in a <code>swing_dates</code> table (which has unique entries)
and associated with <code>events</code> via a join table: <code>event_swing_dates</code> <em>(Don&rsquo;t do this. If you can believe it, this was done in an attempt to speed up database queries)</em>.</p>

<p>The thought of transforming this data at the SQL level gives me a headache. Fortunately in the old app this complexity is hidden under the hood and events just have a <code>#dates</code> method which pulls out the relevant list. For the sake of sanity, my import solution needs to take advantage of that method - hence doing the transformation at the application level using migrations.</p>

<h2>Step 0: Convert the old app to use postgres</h2>

<p>I had never gotten around to updating the old app to use posgres in development, so the first step was to sort that out. Luckily this is pretty easy:</p>

<ol>
<li>In the <code>Gemfile</code>, remove the <code>sqlite3</code> gem and move the <code>pg</code> gem out of the production group.</li>
<li>In <code>database.yml</code>, change the sqlite config to a posgres config</li>
</ol>


<h2>Step 1: Create migrations</h2>

<p>I used a number of migrations to do the data transformation. Since some of them are irreversible, there&rsquo;s no real reason to separate them out, other than organising the code:</p>

<h3>ChangeVenuesToNewFormat</h3>

<p>The venues table isn&rsquo;t changing much so this just involved renaming a column, adding some not-null constraints (probably not necessary) and dropping the columns which aren&rsquo;t being imported yet (<a href="https://github.com/dgmstuart/Swing-Out-London/blob/01df37393444e4d3e217c870d6b3164e001288f0/db/migrate/20140820003740_change_venues_to_new_format.rb">source</a>)</p>

<h3>CreateNewEventsTables</h3>

<p>This involved copying the section of the schema in the new app which creates the tables for the <code>event_seeds</code> and <code>event_generators</code> tables. This way the tables are exactly the same as the new schema. (<a href="https://github.com/dgmstuart/Swing-Out-London/blob/9069b2d1b4103b781a7b3e9951317c40c1d3fb2b/db/migrate/20140820082042_create_new_events_tables.rb">source</a>)</p>

<h3>MoveDataToNewEventTables</h3>

<p>This is where the gnarly stuff happens. First I need a way of putting data into the new tables. I could go and create full models in the app, but it&rsquo;s possible to just create lightweight classes right in the migration:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class EventSeed &lt;  ActiveRecord::Base
  belongs_to :event
  belongs_to :venue
end
class EventGenerator &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  belongs_to :event_seed
end
</code></pre>

<p>I guess I should maybe also have included all of the validations here, but I&rsquo;m fairly confident that the validations are basically equivalent between the two apps, and in any case, the relevant fields have <code>null: false</code> constraints on them in the database, so I&rsquo;m not going to sweat it.</p>

<p>Now we can actually create the new records:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">def change
  Event.all.each do |event|
    event_seed = create_event_seed(event)

    if event.frequency == 1
      start_date = event.first_date || Date.new(2001,1,1)
      create_event_generator(1, start_date, event, event_seed)
    else
      event.dates.each do |date|
        create_event_generator(0, date, event, event_seed) if date &gt; Date.today
      end
    end
  end

  # ...
end
</code></pre>

<p>Note the use of <code>event.dates</code>.</p>

<p><code>create_event_seed</code> and <code>create_event_generator</code> are just wrappers around
<code>EventGenerator.create</code> and <code>EventSeed.create</code> for convenience.</p>

<p>This migration also dropped most of the fields on <code>events</code> but kept the original ids intact - I have a feeling that will turn out to be useful later on. (<a href="https://github.com/dgmstuart/Swing-Out-London/blob/01df37393444e4d3e217c870d6b3164e001288f0/db/migrate/20140820082444_move_data_to_new_event_tables.rb">source</a>)</p>

<h3>CreateNonMigrationTables and DropUnusedTables</h3>

<p>These migrations create the remaining missing tables (like Users, which we&rsquo;re not going to import data into) and drop the tables which don&rsquo;t yet have any counterpart in the new app. (<a href="https://github.com/dgmstuart/Swing-Out-London/blob/01df37393444e4d3e217c870d6b3164e001288f0/db/migrate/20140820210352_create_non_migration_tables.rb">source 1</a>, <a href="https://github.com/dgmstuart/Swing-Out-London/blob/01df37393444e4d3e217c870d6b3164e001288f0/db/migrate/20140820210653_drop_unused_tables.rb">source 2</a>)</p>

<p>Given that in the end I only migrated data from specific tables, this probably wasn&rsquo;t necessary, but it&rsquo;s handy to be able to verify that the schemas between the old and new app exactly match, and to see what hasn&rsquo;t been migrated yet.</p>

<h2>Step 2: Run the migrations on the live database</h2>

<p>So we&rsquo;ve now got a set of migrations which convert the old schema into the latest version of the new schema. Time to test it out on some real data.</p>

<p>Getting a database dump from heroku is easy. You first need to drop the existing development database with <code>dbdrop soldn1_dev</code> and then you can create a new one as a copy of the live database. For me that looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>heroku pg:pull HEROKU_POSTGRESQL_GRAY soldn1_dev
</code></pre>

<p>Then it&rsquo;s just a case of <code>rake db:migrate</code> and cross your fingers. If it&rsquo;s successful then the <code>schema.rb</code> files should match between the old and new app (perhaps modulo some indexes).</p>

<h2>Step 3: Dump the data</h2>

<p>So now we&rsquo;ve got our data into the form we want it, how do we actually move it into the new database?</p>

<p>Dumping the whole database would mean we&rsquo;d carry over the <code>schema_migrations</code> table as well. <code>schema_migrations</code> consists of a list of identifiers which match up to an app&rsquo;s migration files - it&rsquo;s what Rails uses to track which migrations have been run, which is important for e.g. <code>rake db</code> commands, so we don&rsquo;t want to modify it.</p>

<p>The simplest approach seems to be to dump only the tables which actually contain data which we want to migrate:</p>

<pre><code>pg_dump soldn1_dev -a -t event_generators -t event_seeds -t events -t venues &gt; dump
</code></pre>

<p><code>pg_dump</code> actually writes to <code>stdout</code>, so that <code>&gt; dump</code> creates a file from the output.</p>

<p>The <code>-a</code> flag tells <code>pg_dump</code> to dump only the data. Although we&rsquo;ve engineered a state where the migrations on the old site and the new site both result in the same schema, it seems cleaner to only move across the data rather than recreating the tables.</p>

<h2>Step 4: Import the data</h2>

<p>If there are any records already in the relevant tables with IDs which would clash with data in the import then this would need to be resolved somehow before importing. I don&rsquo;t care about any existing data, so I&rsquo;m happy to resolve it by clearing out any existing records with <code>rake db:reset</code>.</p>

<p>To load the data from the dump file:</p>

<pre><code>psql soldn2_dev &lt; dump
</code></pre>

<p>And that&rsquo;s it: the data is now in the new database. Job done.</p>

<p><em>Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/zeeraw">@zeeraw</a> for the suggestion to use Rails migrations</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a New App on Heroku Really Is Stupidly Easy]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/08/15/creating-a-new-app-on-heroku-is-stupidly-easy/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-15T13:49:11+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/08/15/creating-a-new-app-on-heroku-is-stupidly-easy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<pre><code>heroku apps:create swingoutlondon2 --region eu
git push heroku master
heroku run rake db:migrate
</code></pre>

<p>Done *. <a href="https://swingoutlondon2.herokuapp.com">https://swingoutlondon2.herokuapp.com</a> exists.</p>

<p>I know it&rsquo;s been around for ages, but it really is amazing how simple it is.</p>

<p><em>* Actually not quite done - I still needed to:</em></p>

<ul>
<li><em>set up my <a href="https://devcenter.heroku.com/changelog-items/426">secret tokens</a></em></li>
<li><em>jump through a couple of hoops to get Devise&rsquo;s key to be recognised because <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/19832218/failing-to-find-envsecret-key-in-devise-setup-on-heroku#comment35154876_19833145">Heroku doesn&rsquo;t have access to the Rails environment when deploying</a></em></li>
<li><em><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/17082720/1035431">tweak my production.rb</a> to get it to compile assets</em></li>
</ul>


<p><em>But whatever. Hush.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
