<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Development | dgms code]]></title>
  <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/categories/development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-28T13:50:03+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Duncan Stuart]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[dgmstuart@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Better Way of Writing Commit Messages]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/06/23/a-better-way-of-writing-commit-messages/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-23T23:52:20+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/06/23/a-better-way-of-writing-commit-messages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve always tended to write commit messages by answering the question &ldquo;What did I do?&rdquo;, but I learned a different approach recently which tends to produce much more expressive commits, which are often more terse as well. Compare the following:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>&ldquo;What did I do?&rdquo; </th>
<th> &ldquo;What do things look like now?&rdquo;</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Fixed a bug whereby active links were displaying in the wrong colour </td>
<td> Active links now display as blue</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Changed the styling of the popup for clarity </td>
<td> The popup now more clearly displays the review description</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fixed styling bug in previous commit </td>
<td> The styling added in the previous commit now only gets applied to the modal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Added a list of reviewed versions with icons to the security column </td>
<td> The security column now displays a list of reviewed versions</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Ok, so not all of these are fantastic commit messages (they&rsquo;re all real from recent work I&rsquo;ve done). This approach isn&rsquo;t a magic formula but it helps me to focus on what&rsquo;s most relevant, and I feel like the messages on the right are more useful.</p>

<p>An important insight is that although at the time the distinction between implementing a feature/fixing a bug/adding a tweak seems important, when scanning through a list of commits, it&rsquo;s probably the actual behaviour which which is going to be most useful <em>(caveat: if you have a story ID or ticket reference then it&rsquo;s probably worth including)</em>.</p>

<p><em>Props for the tip go to <a href="https://twitter.com/zeeraw">zeeraw</a> - my colleague at <a href="http://www.dxw.com/">dxw</a></em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
