<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Wordpress | dgms code]]></title>
  <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/categories/wordpress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-27T12:50:23+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Duncan Stuart]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[dgmstuart@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WordCamp Europe 2014 Notes - 3: Styling the WordPress Admin]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/09/27/wordcamp-europe-2014-notes-3-styling-the-wordpress-admin/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-27T11:32:55+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/09/27/wordcamp-europe-2014-notes-3-styling-the-wordpress-admin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I&rsquo;m at <a href="http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/">WordCamp Europe</a> in Sofia - taking rough notes on some of the talks</em></p>

<p>Konstantin Dankov <a href="http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/session/konstantin-dankov/">http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/session/konstantin-dankov/</a></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Why style the admin?</p>

<ul>
<li>make things simpler for the user</li>
<li>save time by optimising workflows - supporting power users - removing unnecessary steps: e.g. jump straight to a particular page.</li>
<li>Branding - sometimes larger organisations would like their own branding inside

<ul>
<li>Important to not go overboard! Use a little to do a lot.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Why NOT to do it</p>

<ul>
<li>There&rsquo;s a large cost to supporting it:

<ul>
<li>There&rsquo;s a lot of it!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Clashes with plugin styles: can cause plugins to break</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Consider the experience of editors vs admins</p></li>
<li><p>Adding a custom post type</p>

<ul>
<li>Defaults (all overridable when registering the post type)

<ul>
<li>It goes to the bottom of the list</li>
<li>It has the same icon as other post</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Using filters the order of menu items can be managed in a more coherent way: explicitly naming the order rather than using index numbers.</p></li>
<li><p>Preference: When the custom post type is specific to that project then this menu-modifying code should be in the theme, along with the post type itself: moving it out into a plugin just adds complexity.</p></li>
<li><p>Removing the dashboard to jump straight to the posts: useful if your primary thing is generating new content</p></li>
<li><p>There&rsquo;s a lot of complexity in the WP admin css: responsive styles, Right->Left styles. Making modifications are a lot more work than they look</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
