<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Wordcampeurope | dgms code]]></title>
  <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/categories/wordcampeurope/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-23T17:11:51+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Duncan Stuart]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[dgmstuart@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WordCamp Europe 2014 Notes - 2.5: Matt Mullenweg Q&amp;A]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/09/28/wordcamp-europe-2014-notes-2-dot-5-matt-mullenweg-q-and-a/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-28T12:28:13+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/09/28/wordcamp-europe-2014-notes-2-dot-5-matt-mullenweg-q-and-a</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I&rsquo;m at <a href="http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/">WordCamp Europe</a> in Sofia - taking rough notes on some of the talks</em></p>

<p>Matt Mullenweg, Om Malik <a href="http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/session/matt-mullenweg/">http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/session/matt-mullenweg/</a></p>

<p><img src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/Byng_nfIgAErGt4.jpg" alt="Matt Mullenweg in conversation with Om Malik" /></p>

<h2>In conversation with Om Malik:</h2>

<ul>
<li>Biggest learning in the last 11 years?

<ul>
<li>The community makes it what it is - not the feature set. Lots of other software checks the same boxes that WordPress checks, but it doesn&rsquo;t have what we have in this room</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>For-profits have a limit in their vision. Non-profits have difficulty making connections with enough/the right people. Working together they can achieve more.</li>
<li>&ldquo;I&rsquo;d rather put things into the world under moral licences than immoral ones&rdquo; - GPL is the &ldquo;Most moral licence&rdquo; that you can put software out under</li>
<li>&ldquo;I&rsquo;d be skeptical of an open source company that kept everyone in the same office&rdquo; - that&rsquo;s missing part of the benefit: Open source works when people are all around the world.</li>
<li>How do we structure WP so that it can adapt to what the trends are over the coming years?

<ul>
<li>more and more access is on closed proprietary devices (iphones etc.)</li>
<li>Wp wasn&rsquo;t designed with touch interaction in mind. WP apps haven&rsquo;t had a ton of community involvement</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BynhzoPIMAAwoDT.jpg" alt="Photo of Matt Mullenweg Q&amp;A by @Joan_Artes on twitter" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="https://twitter.com/Joan_Artes/status/516191909656920065/photo/1">@Joan_Artes</a></em></p>

<h2>Q&amp;A</h2>

<ul>
<li>What are your thoughts about entrepreneurship in Europe, particularly eastern europe?

<ul>
<li>@om - Local laws in Europe favour local investors over international investors: a challenge for entrepreneurship</li>
<li>&ldquo;The best thing European companies can do is to stop comparing themselves to American companies&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>CFTP Wheatley: &ldquo;You&rsquo;ve scaled up 1800 people - what do those people actually do&rdquo;

<ul>
<li>Lots on support</li>
<li>Design and development: allows us to contribute much much more to WP Core</li>
<li>&ldquo;I want to scale that as far as it can go&rdquo;</li>
<li>Wants it to be an exemplar of a mixed nonprofit/for profit: prove to the world that it <em>Can</em> be done.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Once we have APIs it will enable a whole new class of application - e.g. front-ends which talk to something which isn&rsquo;t WP but implements the WP API.

<ul>
<li>A Cambrian explosion for WordPress - comparable to when plugins were introduced</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>&ldquo;We&rsquo;ve found the search in WP isn&rsquo;t very good&rdquo;

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;No it&rsquo;s terrible&rdquo;</li>
<li>If you&rsquo;re serious about search you should use a plugin that indexes your content in lucene or elasticsearch</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>No plans now or in the future to have paid plugins - or a paid app store.

<ul>
<li>Could make things more discoverable: look at what you&rsquo;ve got installed and suggest things you might find useful</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>This year there were more non-english downloads than english downloads

<ul>
<li>More translations will be the biggest driver of increases in WP usage</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>How much should WP businesses be contributing to the WP community?

<ul>
<li>Maybe 5%, so if you have 100 employees, 5 of them could be contributing to core.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Can we get rid of Backwards compatibility

<ul>
<li>I don&rsquo;t buy that we should break backwards compatibility for architectural purity. More inclined to do it for reasons that will mean more people use WP</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lots of plugins aren&rsquo;t maintained - some maintainers may even have died. Can we get these just removed from the directory?

<ul>
<li>Plugins over 2 years old will stop showing up in search results</li>
<li>Plugin search is going to be optimised towards putting the most popular, best supported ones at the top.</li>
<li>Factor in the compatibility between plugins - plugins which work well together</li>
<li>Plugins are the most open area for innovation - it&rsquo;s an open market</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WordCamp Europe 2014 Notes - 2.4: Code Deodorant]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/09/28/wordcamp-europe-2014-notes-2-dot-4-code-deodorant/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-28T10:27:07+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/09/28/wordcamp-europe-2014-notes-2-dot-4-code-deodorant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I&rsquo;m at <a href="http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/">WordCamp Europe</a> in Sofia - taking rough notes on some of the talks</em></p>

<p>Tom Nowell (cftp) <a href="http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/session/tom-nowell/">http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/session/tom-nowell/</a></p>

<ul>
<li>Now when running vanilla WP without plugins you shouldn&rsquo;t see any warnings, so all warnings are things you should pay attention to</li>
<li>&lsquo;@&rsquo; swallows errors - hides them.</li>
<li><a href="http://codex.wordpress.org/Plugin_API/Action_Reference/pre_get_posts">pre_get_posts action</a> - useful for removing complexity: modifying queries before they get run</li>
<li>Law of Demeter &ldquo;if you&rsquo;re talking to something, only talk to the things directly adjacent to you&rdquo;</li>
<li>No global variables - random ordering of tests can help to show up issues.</li>
<li>Tools for code quality:

<ul>
<li>php syntax checking - if your editor isn&rsquo;t doing this you&rsquo;re doing it wrong. PHP Storm does this</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/squizlabs/PHP_CodeSniffer">php code sniffer</a> - give it coding standards - it&rsquo;ll check them</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Halleck45/PhpMetrics">php Metrics</a></li>
<li>phpLOC - tells you how many lines, classes, namespaces, measure of code complexity</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/phpmd/phpmd">php Mess detector</a> - fuzzy matching: helps detect typos and join up e.g. misspelled variables which might be the same thing</li>
<li>NPath &amp; Cyclomatic complexity - Cycl = number of points at which code may diverge, NPath is number of execution paths through the code.

<ul>
<li>NPath complexity is roughly equivalent to the number of unit tests that you need to have to fully test the function</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lots of WP functions have incredibly large npath complexity - WP_Query::get_posts is insanely large. Even larger in WP 4.0

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.tomjn.com/390/wp_queryget_posts/">http://www.tomjn.com/390/wp_queryget_posts/</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WordCamp Europe 2014 Notes - 2.3: The Next Generation Hosting Stack]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/09/28/wordcamp-europe-2014-notes-2-dot-3-the-next-generation-hosting-stack/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-28T09:33:02+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/09/28/wordcamp-europe-2014-notes-2-dot-3-the-next-generation-hosting-stack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I&rsquo;m at <a href="http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/">WordCamp Europe</a> in Sofia - taking rough notes on some of the talks</em></p>

<p>Mark Jaquith (@markjaquith) <a href="http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/session/mark-jaquith/">http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/session/mark-jaquith/</a></p>

<ul>
<li>Why is performance important?

<ul>
<li>It&rsquo;s not about overall speed - it&rsquo;s about the frustration of being interrupted</li>
<li>Everyone hates Lag</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>WP has a bad rep for speed

<ul>
<li>no matter what wp core do, WP DB&rsquo;s are getting bigger, lots of functionality, lots of plugins</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>WP is dynamic - everything is built on the fly

<ul>
<li>Why don&rsquo;t we just generate static files? - No persistent caching in core. Pages are so dynamic: search results etc. Only a small number of pages can be cached</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>For the purposes of this talk: speed = speed of download of just the html page (not css or other assets)</li>
<li>3+ seconds = EMERGENCY</li>
<li>1-3 seconds = Slow</li>
<li>100-250ms = fast</li>
<li>&lt;100ms = instant</li>
<li>Many hosts don&rsquo;t help with static caching</li>
<li>Virtual server hosting - what to look for

<ul>
<li>Are they going to be around for a while?</li>
<li>What&rsquo;s their raw performance - lots of people have done hardcore speed tests - easily googleable</li>
<li>Value for money</li>
<li>Tool support - provisioning scripts, auto backup</li>
<li>Recommended: Linode, Digital Ocean</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Web Server</h2>

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;Nginx is the best thing to happen to web servers ever&rdquo;</li>
<li>Apache approach - php is baked in. That means there&rsquo;s an overhead for each request</li>
<li>Nginx approach - can&rsquo;t have php baked in. PHP-FPM runs php</li>
<li>PHP 5.5 has significant performance improvements over previous versions</li>
<li>HHVM - facebook project: transcodes php into machine code on the fly, with caching = crazy fast

<ul>
<li>Might not be production stable - need monitoring to catch when it crashes</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Database</h2>

<ul>
<li>MySQL is not the only option: MariaDB, Percona</li>
<li>HyperDB - project for providing a layer to manage lots of database instances</li>
</ul>


<h2>Caching</h2>

<h3>Page caching:</h3>

<ul>
<li>Questions - who, what, how long. Answers: Anonymous???, front of site, minutes, maybe hours???.</li>
<li>Nginx has a cache</li>
<li>Varnish is another option, but is another moving part</li>
<li>Plugins are tightly integrated with WP, but run in php so are much slower</li>
</ul>


<h3>Object caching:</h3>

<ul>
<li>Recommend using Redis (Pantheon uses it)</li>
<li>Memcached - used to be a recommendation. Restarting flushes the data - can cause massive spikes in load</li>
<li>Mark&rsquo;s wrappers:

<ul>
<li>TLC Tranients <a href="http://bitly/tlc-transients">http://bitly/tlc-transients</a></li>
<li>Fragment caching: <a href="http://bitly/fragment-cache">http://bitly/fragment-cache</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h3>The next generation stack</h3>

<p><img src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/Bym-26pCcAAyPVd.jpg:large" alt="The next generation WordPress hosting stack" /></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Audience qu Hyper db - works with MariaDB &amp; Percona?</p>

<ul>
<li>AFAIK yes</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>My qu - can you make core use Redis for your object cache or is that just for your own caching</p>

<ul>
<li>Yes - you configure an object cache and core will use it to cache posts, taxonomies, a bunch of other things.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Audience qu: What do you use for performance monitoring</p>

<ul>
<li>NewRelic: very expensive, but gives you amazing insights</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>*</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WordCamp Europe 2014 Notes - 1.8: Usability Testing]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/09/27/wordcamp-europe-2014-notes-8-usability-testing/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-27T15:15:07+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/09/27/wordcamp-europe-2014-notes-8-usability-testing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I&rsquo;m at <a href="http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/">WordCamp Europe</a> in Sofia - taking rough notes on some of the talks</em></p>

<p>Dario Jazbec Hrvatin - <a href="http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/session/dario-jazbec-hrvatin/">http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/session/dario-jazbec-hrvatin/</a></p>

<p><img src="http://photos-e.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xaf1/10665594_1562716813952100_214832350_n.jpg" alt="sketchnotes by @studionetting" /></p>

<p><em>Awesome sketchnotes by <a href="http://instagram.com/p/tc-b8atkPN/">@studionetting</a></em></p>

<ul>
<li>Remote user testing</li>
<li>Google hangouts or Skype

<ul>
<li>Important to make sure that your users are comfortable with the tech before officially starting the test</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Beginners or Experts as your users: depends what you&rsquo;re testing</li>
<li><p>Have a 5 minute chat to screen them: make sure that they meet your profile - that they will provide useful data</p></li>
<li><p>Scenarios: Start with the test (specific task that they need to do) then work it up into a scenario</p></li>
<li>Start off with a script</li>
<li>after that - relax them: get them talking by asking some simple questions:

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;what are your favourite themes and plugins&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t be afraid to just skip a step if they&rsquo;re struggling</li>
<li><p>To close off the session:</p>

<ul>
<li>Ask any addition questions</li>
<li>answer any questions they have</li>
<li>thank them (!!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Throughout: Keep a poker face</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WordCamp Europe 2014 Notes - 1.7: Interactive Prototyping]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/09/27/wordcamp-europe-2014-notes-7-interactive-prototyping/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-27T14:40:38+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2014/09/27/wordcamp-europe-2014-notes-7-interactive-prototyping</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I&rsquo;m at <a href="http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/">WordCamp Europe</a> in Sofia - taking rough notes on some of the talks</em></p>

<p>Karin Christen <a href="http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/session/karin-christen/">http://2014.europe.wordcamp.org/session/karin-christen/</a></p>

<p><img src="http://photos-e.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xaf1/10665594_1562716813952100_214832350_n.jpg" alt="sketchnotes by @studionetting" /></p>

<p><em>Awesome sketchnotes by <a href="http://instagram.com/p/tc-b8atkPN/">@studionetting</a></em></p>

<ul>
<li>Used dynamic style guide - one page in the prototype</li>
<li>Started in the browser right from the beginning - speed benefits but also:

<ul>
<li>responsiveness from the beginning</li>
<li>easy reference for the existing styles</li>
<li>visual specification - communication tool</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Prototypes = a basis for a specification for user testing</li>
<li>php doesn&rsquo;t work for dynamic prototypes - just html/css</li>
<li>Made a prototype Generator (in js?)

<ul>
<li>Installs quickly</li>
<li>Dynamic content without php (how??)</li>
<li>Benefit: less noise from php</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://vuejs.org/">http://vuejs.org/</a>

<ul>
<li>Adds attributes which can be added to markup which can e.g. optionally show and hide elements based on url query params</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Closing comment: &ldquo;The modern prototype is a living playground, not a project milestone&rdquo;</p></li>
<li><p>Audience question - if you&rsquo;re using wp - why don&rsquo;t you just jump into wp? Why go to the effort of generating content in JS?</p>

<ul>
<li>Answer: the project example was for a complex back-end which didn&rsquo;t exist yet. With WP their process is slightly different: start off designing in the browser (test there?), then port over to WP (once it&rsquo;s validated?)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>My question - how do you deal with responsive elements when you don&rsquo;t know what the context will be: media queries only work with the whole size of the page.</p>

<ul>
<li>Answer: we design in context</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
